Guide to the Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc., Board of Editors Records 1949-1968
University of Chicago Library
Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc., Board of Editors. Records
1949-1968
1 linear foot (2 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc., Board of Editors Records consists of minutes from of board meetings from 1949 to 1959. Also included are newspaper clippings, magazines, typescripts, and memoranda concerning the Encyclopaedia Britannica through 1968.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Historical Note
The Encyclopaedia Britannica was founded in 1788 by a “Society of Gentlemen in Scotland.” It became the property of Sears, Rosebuck & Co. in 1920 under Julius Rosenwald. Though offered in February 1943 to the University of Chicago, it was instead personally acquired by the University’s vice president, William Benton. The University’s faculty became involved with the production of the Encyclopaedia, including Chancellor Robert M. Hutchins, who took a leave of absence in 1946 to guide the adult education program of the Encyclopaedia. During these years, the Encyclopaedia’s title pages noted that it was "edited with the advice of the faculties of the University of Chicago."
Scope Note
The Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc., Board of Editors Records consists of minutes from its meetings covering the years 1949 to 1959. Also included in this collection are newspaper clippings, magazines, typescripts, and memoranda concerning the Encyclopaedia Britannica through 1968.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
William Benton. Papers.
Robert M. Hutchins. Papers
Julius Rosenwald. Papers
Subject Headings
Encyclopaedia Britannica, inc. Board of Editors; University of Chicago -- Administration; University of Chicago -- Finance; Encyclopaedia Britannica, inc. -- History; Encyclopedias and dictionaries
INVENTORY
- Meeting minutes, 1949-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Meeting minutes, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Meeting minutes, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Meeting minutes, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Meeting minutes, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Meeting minutes, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Meeting minutes, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Meeting minutes, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Meeting minutes, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous, Invitations to the 175th Anniversary of the Encyclopaedia Britannica Notices for 1968 Encyclopaedia Britannica Lectures at the University of Chicago Know Magazine, Fall 1966 Newspaper clippings Contributor’s guide, typescript and pamphlet Preface, Memorandum regarding acquisition of Encyclopaedia Britannica by the University of Chicago, January 1961, typescript (Box 2, Folder 5)